<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Zahlblog</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/</link><description>Ramblings of a veteran Pythonista with a passion for refactoring and education.</description><atom:link href="https://zahlman.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022-2025 &lt;a href="mailto:zahlman@proton.me"&gt;Karl Knechtel&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 14:43:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>New year, new blog</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2025/01/01/new-year-new-blog/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;You're not imagining things - the blog has a whole new look, in large part as a result of switching to the &lt;a href="https://getnikola.com"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; site generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2025/01/01/new-year-new-blog/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2025/01/01/new-year-new-blog/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> `fixup! added list`</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/31/todo-list-2/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;The rest of the TODOwl&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy new year to all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's post is about a folder on my desktop named &lt;code&gt;dev&lt;/code&gt;. It's where I've kept (for many years, well into my Windows-using days, even into the era when I used SVN rather than Git) all my working copies for my own projects (and forks of others'), mostly Python code of course. (I'm not sure how I organized things at the time, but there are projects in there dating back to 2006.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/31/todo-list-2/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (20 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/31/todo-list-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> Python packaging: Why we can't have nice things, Part 1</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/24/python-packaging-1/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;The old refrain&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is a start of a series I've planned about how packaging currently works in Python, what's wrong with it, and how to cope with the problems. But before I get into the meat of it, I want to talk about common complaints that &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; resonate with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/24/python-packaging-1/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (21 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/24/python-packaging-1/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> `# TODO: finish todo list`</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/20/todo-finish-todo-list/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;&lt;code&gt;# TODO: finish todo list&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a difficult post to write, largely because of the self-critique involved. Which is part of why I've been putting it off. For months, if I'm honest with myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But putting it off has only made it harder to write. I also seem to have reached a point where it psychologically feels impossible to publish anything else here first. So, I'm finally forcing myself to write it now - during the holiday season, to prove to myself that I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's no secret that the history of this blog so far has been dominantly one of false starts. Please allow me a moment to explain how that came to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/20/todo-finish-todo-list/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/12/20/todo-finish-todo-list/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> An open letter to the PSF CoC WG, addendum 1/n</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/08/10/open-letter-psf-coc-wg-addendum-1-tim-peters/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;The Suspension of Tim Peters&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who contacted me with praise, thanks etc. for &lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/politics/the-psf/2024/07/31/an-open-letter-to-the-psf-coc-wg.html"&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;, or shared the link. I'm truly grateful for all such support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't seen that post yet, please take a moment to read it first. It gives important context (such as explanations of acronyms), which I will not be repeating here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On August 7, Python core developer Tim Peters was issued a 3-month (although it ended November 1, perhaps due to a clerical error) suspension from that role, accompanied by a suspension from the &lt;a href="https://discuss.python.org"&gt;official Python Discourse forum&lt;/a&gt;. This was connected to my own (permanent) ban from that forum (issued July 19), a fact which other sources have largely ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I describe key events between those two dates, tell my story, and respond to the charges laid against Mr. Peters (spoiler: I find them ludicrous).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/08/10/open-letter-psf-coc-wg-addendum-1-tim-peters/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (13 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/08/10/open-letter-psf-coc-wg-addendum-1-tim-peters/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> An open letter to the PSF CoC WG</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/07/31/an-open-letter-to-the-psf-coc-wg/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;On July 19th, I was banned ("indefinitely suspended") from the official Python Discourse forum, and several of my most recent posts were "temporarily" hidden by flagging "by the community" (per the stock phrasing of the Discourse software). I was already voluntarily about to leave, so I don't particularly mind losing access - but it was nevertheless unjust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the manner in which this was handled shocks and appalls me. In my estimation, the WG has acted with &lt;em&gt;astounding&lt;/em&gt; hypocrisy, which I will allude to in this post and attempt to elucidate in later posts. In announcing my ban, they made a parting statement which misrepresents my position in egregious and indefensible ways. Further, it is my considered opinion that these actions reflect a "social justice" ideology which is neither just nor eusocial - one which I believe is fundamentally corrupt and enables serious real-world harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/07/31/an-open-letter-to-the-psf-coc-wg/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (14 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/07/31/an-open-letter-to-the-psf-coc-wg/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> Where I've been</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/05/09/where-ive-been/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow (in my timezone) is my birthday, so I wanted to get a post in while I'm still 42. I see it's been another 13 months since my previous posts - hopefully I can break that pattern this year. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy"&gt;Fittingly&lt;/a&gt;, it feels like I've discovered some profound answers in the past year, and yet I'm still left with lots of research to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/05/09/where-ive-been/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2024/05/09/where-ive-been/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> Ah yes, I'm back, by the way</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2023/04/09/ah-yes-im-back-by-the-way/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attentive readers of my previous post may have found the following bit odd:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had originally planned to write about this for the module's 19th anniversary - as my second post on this blog - before I got distracted from the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;given that it &lt;em&gt;actually was&lt;/em&gt; my second post on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2023/04/09/ah-yes-im-back-by-the-way/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2023/04/09/ah-yes-im-back-by-the-way/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> Timing</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2023/04/06/timing/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had originally planned to write about this for the module's 19th anniversary - as my second post on this blog - before I got distracted from the project. (Long story short, I never actually abandoned the idea - it's just hard to get back into things sometimes.) I've now missed both that anniversary and the 20th. One might say my own sense of timing is not so great - but so it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2023/04/06/timing/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (11 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2023/04/06/timing/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title> Welcome to the ZahlBlog</title><link>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2022/03/02/welcome/</link><dc:creator>Karl Knechtel</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Since I'm also passionate about teaching programming, I'll also be trying to give insight into the process of learning Python, and teaching Python. Later I also intend to include some articles aimed at troubleshooting specific, common problems that beginners have - in a format like Stack Overflow, except that I get to control the questions as well. My long term goal is to write a book.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://zahlman.github.io/posts/2022/03/02/welcome/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>